Fred G. Rounds Papers 1918-1967
Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections, Washington State University Libraries
Fred G. Rounds Papers
1918-1967
Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections, Washington State University Libraries http://www.libraries.wsu.edu/masc Terrell Library P.O. Box 645610 Pullman 99164-5610 mascref@wsu.edu http://www.libraries.wsu.edu/masc
Cage 231
9 linear feet 18 boxes, plus oversize.
Includes correspondence, reports, and photographs concerning civic organizations, civil defense, land-use planning, the Pullman (Wash.) planning commission, the Kiwanis Club, and a number of residential architectural projects.
Fred Grafton Rounds was born January 6, 1893, at St. Paul, Minnesota. He was graduated from the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign in 1916. During the First World War, Rounds was commissioned a 2nd Lieutenant in the U.S. Army. He was discharged as a 1st Lieutenant in April 1919. Rounds began his career in architecture for the firm of Croft and Hoerner Architects,in Minneapolis. In 1923, Rounds joined the WSC Department of Architectural Engineering in 1923, where he served as an assistant professor of architecture and as an assistant designer in the college architect's office. He also joined with his colleague, Stanley A. Smith, in the architectural firm of Smith and Rounds. The partnership designed many residences in Pullman in the late 1920s, along with several sorority and fraternity houses. By the late 1920s, Rounds left his post at WSC to pursue a full-time private architecture practice in Tacoma and Chehalis.
In 1932 he designed the center unit addition to the Pullman High School. In 1934 he returned to the WSC campus to oversee several college building construction project sponsored by the federal Public Works Administration. From 1937 to 1950, Rounds he served as superintendent of the State College's Department of Buildings and Grounds. He retired from WSC in 1958. Fred G. Rounds was a civic-minded resident of Pullman. He joined the local Kiwanis club, serving on numerous committees. He was elected its president in 1943, and in 1955 served as the Pacific Northwest District Governor. In addition, Rounds was an organizer and long-time member of the Planning Commission and the Whitman County Planning Commission. He served on the Pullman School Board and the Pullman Memorial Hospital Board; and he was director of the Pullman-WSC Civil Defense program and chairman of the Pullman Chamber of Commerce. Rounds was a member of the Pullman Community Congregational Church, where he served as a deacon and as chief usher. He also oversaw the design and construction of the congregation's new house of worship in the mid-1950s. He was also active in Masonic lodges. In 1919, Rounds married the former Ruth Wikoff. The union brought three children, Mrs. Harold (Jeanne) Olsen, Mrs. Earl (Margery) Muir, and Fred G. Rounds, Jr. Ruth Rounds died in 1949. In 1955, Fred Rounds married the former Mrs. John P. (Dora) Sanger. Rounds died on May 2, 1972.
The papers of Fred G. Rounds consist of correspondence, reports, enclosures, and photographs concerning civic organizations, civil defence, land-use planning, employment at Washington State College, and Rounds' private architectural contracts. The larger and more significant series concern the Pullman City Planning Commission, the Kiwanis Club, and a number of residential architectural projects done as private contracts. Most materials date from about 1940 to about 1960. The papers are arranged in nine series, reflecting an apparent original order. Within series, the arrangement is alphabetical subject folders.
Series list: Series 1. Personal and Professional Correspondence Series 2. Kiwanis Series 3. Planning--local, county, and region Series 4. Civil Defense Series 5. Community Congregational Church Series 6. Pullman and WSC Series 7. Humor Series 8. Social Clubs and other Organizations Series 9. Miscellaneous
The collection is open and available for on-site research use. Researchers will be instructed to wear gloves. Though the images vary widely in their physical condition, reproductions in the form of digital scans and prints will be available for most of the items in the collection.
Washington State University Libraries acquired the Fred G. Rounds Papers in two accessions, the first prior to 1970 and the second (MS 75-7) in May 1975, from the WSU School of Architecture. The drawings in folder 276 were received later, with a collection of architectural drawings from the Pullman Community Congregational Church (MS.2008.28), and added to this collection in 2018.
Washington State University--Faculty--Archives; Architecture--Washington (State)--Pullman.; Civil defense--Washington (State)--Pullman--1950-1960.
City Planning
- Personal and Professional Correspondence, 1
  - H. H. Waples, personal, 1934-1936 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - H. H. Waples, Treasury Department, 1934-1935 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Chapin Foster, Sec.-Director, Washington State Historical Society, 1944-1947 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Personal Correspondence
    - 1956 (Box-folder 1/4)
    - 1957 (Box-folder 1/5)
    - 1958 (Box-folder 1/6)
    - 1959 (Box-folder 1/7)
    - 1960 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - 1961 (Box-folder 1/9)
    - 1962 (Box-folder 1/10)
    - 1963 (Box-folder 1/11)
    - 1964 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Around the World Trip, 1963 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - College Architect Office Data (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Logan G. Kimsey, M.D., residence, 1940 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - Kappa Sigma House, alterations, 1952 (Box-folder 1/16)
  - Hollingsworth Apartments, alterations, 1953 (Box-folder 2/17)
  - W. W. Durham, High School, Kellogg, Idaho, plans, 1953 (Box-folder 2/18)
  - Kappa Kappa Gamma, porch railing, 1954 (Box-folder 2/19)
  - Ralph Fowler, residence, 1954 (Box-folder 2/20)
  - John S. Peterson, residence, 1954 (Box-folder 2/21)
  - Guy Murchland, residence, 1955 (Box-folder 2/22)
  - Dean Sanders (Box-folder 2/23)
  - Architectural journals and bulletins (Box-folder 2/24)
  - Miscellaneous clippings (Box-folder 2/25)
  - Product brochures (Box-folder 2/26)
  - Associated General Contractors, Spokane, 1953 (Box-folder 2/27)
- Kiwanis, 2
  - Kiwanis, Pullman Club
    - "What Is Kiwanis?", 1960, 1962 inc. (Box-folder 2/28)
    - Membership, 1922-1962 (Box-folder 2/29)
    - Annual officers and members roster, 1940-1965, inc. (Box-folder 2/30)
    - By Laws, Local and International (Box-folder 2/31)
    - Committee on education, fellowship, club history, and laws and regulations (Box-folder 3/32)
    - Support of Churches Division (Box-folder 3/33)
    - Pullman club charter correspondence, 1922 (Box-folder 3/34)
    - "Facts about Pullman Kiwanis Club," prepared by Education Committee, March 1945 (Box-folder 3/35)
    - "Facts about Pullman Kiwanis Club," prepared by Education Committee, May 1947 (Box-folder 3/36)
    - "Annual Achievement Report of the Kiwanis Club of Pullman, for the Year 1938 (Box-folder 3/37)
    - Circle K House, 1938 (Box-folder 3/38)
    - Circle K Fraternity, 1947 (Box-folder 3/39)
    - "Former Members, Deceased or Moved Away," A through K (Box-folder 3/40)
    - Membership (Box-folder 3/41)
    - "Kiwaniquiz", 1962-1963 (Box-folder 3/42)
    - Fred G. Rounds' corr., 1920s (Box-folder 3/43)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box-folder 3/44)
    - Newspaper Clipping Scrapbook, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 3/45)
    - Passion Play, Bryan Hall Auditorium, December 1955 (Box-folder 3/46)
    - Photographs (Box-folder 4/47)
    - Misc. correspondence, 1950s-1960s (Box-folder 4/48)
  - Kiwanis History, including Pullman Weekly Bulletin
    - 1926-1928 and 1935 (Box-folder 4/49)
    - 1940-1954 (Box-folder 4/50)
    - 1955 (Box-folder 4/51)
    - 1956 (Box-folder 4/52)
    - 1957 (Box-folder 4/53)
    - 1958 (Box-folder 4/54)
    - 1959 (Box-folder 4/55)
    - 1960 (Box-folder 4/56)
    - 1961 (Box-folder 4/57)
    - 1962 (Box-folder 5/58)
    - 1963 (Box-folder 5/59)
    - 1964 (Box-folder 5/60)
    - 1965 (Box-folder 5/61)
    - 1966 (Box-folder 5/62)
    - 1967 (Box-folder 5/63)
  - Kiwanis, Pacific Northwest District
    - Board Meeting
      - Seattle, February 1955 (Box-folder 5/64)
      - Seattle, February 1962 (Box-folder 5/65)
      - Seattle, November 1962 (Box-folder 5/66)
      - Portland, January 1963 (Box-folder 5/67)
      - Vancouver, B.C., February 1964 (Box-folder 5/68)
      - Seattle, November 1964 (Box-folder 5/69)
    - District Convention
      - Salem, Oregon, 1956 (Box-folder 5/70)
      - Penticton, B.C., 1957 (Box-folder 5/71)
      - Tacoma, 1958 (Box-folder 5/72)
      - Eugene, 1959 (Box-folder 5/73)
      - Vancouver, B.C., 1960 (Box-folder 5/74)
      - Spokane, 1961 (Box-folder 5/75)
      - Yakima, 1962 (Box-folder 5/76)
      - Anchorage, 1963 (Box-folder 5/77)
      - Portland, 1964 (Box-folder 6/78)
      - Seattle, 1966 (Box-folder 6/79)
  - Kiwanis, International Convention, Denver, 1962 (Box-folder 6/80)
  - Kiwanis, International Convention, Portland, 1966 (Box-folder 6/81)
  - Misc. convention programs (Box-folder 6/82)
  - Kiwanis, Fred G. Rounds, Pacific Northwest District Gov.
    - Election as governor, 1964 (Box-folder 6/83)
    - Personal scrapbook during tenure as district governor (Box-folder 6/84)
    - Pacific Northwest District Audit Report for the period January 1, 1954 to December 31, 1954 (Box-folder 6/85)
    - Governor's Tour of Alaska, 1955 (Box-folder 6/86)
    - New Club Building, 1955 (Box-folder 6/87)
    - New Club Building Committee, 1955 (Box-folder 6/88)
    - Public Relations Committee, 1955 (Box-folder 6/89)
    - Education and Fellowship Committee (Box-folder 6/90)
    - Attendance Committee, 1955 (Box-folder 7/91)
    - Convention Program Committee (Box-folder 7/92)
    - "On to Cleveland," international convention, 1955 (Box-folder 7/93)
    - District Bulletin, 1949-1966, inc. (Box-folder 7/94)
    - District Directory, 1953-1959 (Box-folder 7/95)
    - International Directory, 1956 (Box-folder 7/96)
- Planning--local, county, and regional, 3
  - Pullman Public Schools, Durham Report, 1949, and newspaper clippings (Box-folder 7/97)
  - City-College Relations, Special Committee, 1946 (Box-folder 7/98)
  - Pullman Housing Authority, corr., part 1 (Box-folder 7/99)
  - Pullman Housing Authority, corr., part 2 (Box-folder 7/100)
  - Pullman Community Hospital Board, 1952-1964 (Box-folder 7/101)
  - Pullman, City of Pullman City Plan (Box-folder 7/102)
  - Capital outlay (Box-folder 7/103)
  - Subdivision Ordinance No. A-217 (Box-folder 7/104)
  - Mobile Homes (Box-folder 7/105)
  - Studies and Master Plan, 1960 (Box-folder 8/106)
  - Public Schools (Box-folder 8/107)
  - Bond Issue, 1958 (Box-folder 8/108)
  - Ivan Bloch and Associates, 1957 (Box-folder 8/109)
  - To-do Items (Box-folder 8/110)
  - Misc. (Box-folder 8/111)
  - Photographs (Box-folder 8/112)
  - Pullman City Planning Commission
    - General (Box-folder 8/113)
    - Business and Development Committee, 1960 (Box-folder 8/114)
    - Minutes, 1947-1951 (Box-folder 8/115)
    - Minutes, 1952-1955, inc. (Box-folder 8/116)
    - Minutes, 1956 (Box-folder 8/117)
    - Minutes, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 8/118)
    - Minutes, 1959 (Box-folder 8/119)
    - Minutes, 1960 (Box-folder 8/120)
    - Minutes, 1961 (Box-folder 9/121)
    - Minutes, 1962 (Box-folder 9/122)
    - Minutes, 1963 (Box-folder 9/123)
    - Minutes, 1964 (Box-folder 9/124)
    - Commission and Board of Adjustment Minutes, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 9/125)
    - Fallout Shelters (Box-folder 9/126)
    - Misc. (Box-folder 9/127)
  - Planning, misc. (Box-folder 9/128)
  - Highway Advertising Control (Box-folder 9/129)
  - Association of Washington Cities, corr., 1939-1940 (Box-folder 9/130)
  - City of Pullman, "Budget for 1953" (Box-folder 9/131)
  - "Accident Report Study for the City of Pullman", 1960 (Box-folder 9/132)
  - "Washington Street and Highway Need Study, Report for the City of Pullman", January 1960 (Box-folder 9/133)
  - Master Plan for Pullman, 1957 (Box-folder 9/134)
  - "Hillside Terrace, A Proposed Addition to the City of Pullman, Washington", 1959 (Box-folder 9/135)
  - Pullman, Washington, Zoning Ordinance No. 649, as amended (Box-folder 9/136)
  - "Proposed Zoning Ordinance of the City of Pullman", January 1961 (Box-folder 9/137)
  - "Report of Planning Studies, Pullman, Wash., January 1960" (Box-folder 9/138)
  - Newspaper Clipping Scrapbooks, City of Pullman and misc., building construction (Box-folder 9/139)
  - Whitman County Planning Commission
    - School Consolidation (Box-folder 10/140)
    - "A Comprehensive Outdoor Recreation Plan for Whitman County, Washington," Preliminary Draft, July 31, 1965 (Box-folder 10/141)
    - "Whitman County Agriculture, Washington," County Agricultural Data Series, 1965, by Port of Whitman County (Box-folder 10/142)
    - State Parks and Recreation (Box-folder 10/143)
    - Sub-Division Ordinance (Box-folder 10/144)
    - Trailer Courts and Mobile Homes (Box-folder 10/145)
    - Whitman County Parks and Recreation (Box-folder 10/146)
    - Airport Zoning (Box-folder 10/147)
    - County Zoning (Box-folder 10/148)
    - County Plan, M-1-L Zone (Box-folder 10/149)
    - County Plan, Parks (Box-folder 10/150)
    - County Plan, Parks and Recreation--Wash. State Sportsmen (Box-folder 10/151)
    - County Plan, Public Relations (Box-folder 10/152)
    - Minutes, 1957-1960 (Box-folder 10/153)
    - Minutes, 1961 (Box-folder 10/154)
    - Minutes and misc. (Box-folder 10/155)
    - Weed Control Plan, 1959 (Box-folder 11/156)
    - Reorganization, 1959-1960 (Box-folder 11/157)
    - "The Comprehensive Outdoor Plan for Whitman County, Washington", 1966 (Box-folder 11/158)
    - Misc. corr. (Box-folder 11/159)
    - General, 1961-1965 (Box-folder 11/160)
    - Whitman County Zoning Resolution, 1958 (Box-folder 11/161)
    - County Planning Commission Plan for Whitman County (Box-folder 11/162)
    - Whitman County Plan, to-do (Box-folder 11/163)
    - "County Commissioners' Land Use Planning Guide," Wash. State Assoc. of County Commissioners, May 1959 (Box-folder 11/164)
    - Planning Assoc. of Washington, 1964 convention, Yakima (Box-folder 11/165)
    - Whitman County Port District (Box-folder 11/166)
    - "An Economic Summary and A Comprehensive Plan for the Port of Whitman County," by H. E. Bovay, Jr., Consulting Engineers, 1961 (Box-folder 11/167)
    - "The Port District and the Comprehensive Plan for the Port of Whitman County" (Box-folder 11/168)
    - Inland Waterways Association, corr., 1958 (Box-folder 11/169)
    - Inland Waterways Association, misc. (Box-folder 11/170)
- Civil Defense, 4
  - WSC-Pullman Civil Defense
    - Notices of Meetings and Minutes (Box-folder 12/171)
    - Test Problem No. 1, 1952 (Box-folder 12/172)
    - Yellow Alert, February 24, 1952 (Box-folder 12/173)
    - Red Alert, May 6, 1952 (Box-folder 12/174)
    - "Basic Plan for Civil Defense" (Box-folder 12/175)
    - Misc. (Box-folder 12/176)
    - Moscow-Univ. of Idaho, 1951-1952 (Box-folder 12/177)
    - American Legion Auxiliary (Box-folder 12/178)
    - Clippings, 1952-1960 (Box-folder 12/179)
    - Washington State Defense Council (Box-folder 12/180)
    - WSC, Plan for Civil Defense, 1952 (Box-folder 12/181)
    - WSC, Civil Defense Manual (Box-folder 12/182)
    - Univ. of Washington, "Report Recommending a Division of Safety", 1950 (Box-folder 12/183)
    - Univ. of Washington, Civil Defense (Box-folder 12/184)
    - The Civil Defense Alert (Box-folder 12/185)
    - U.S. Civil Defense Council (Box-folder 12/186)
    - Charts: WSC-Pullman Civil Defense (drafts?), 2 versions, circa 1940s-1950s (Box-folder Oversize / 276)
  - U.S. Civil Defense
    - Publications, order invoices (Box-folder 12/187)
    - Fallout shelters (Box-folder 12/188)
    - National literature, part 1 (Box-folder 12/189)
    - National literature, part 2 (Box-folder 13/190)
    - State of Washington (Box-folder 13/191)
    - Fallout Shelter Design and Evaluation Workshop [1961], Office of Civil and Defense Mobilization (Box-folder 13/192)
- Community Congregational Church, 5
  - Annual reports, 1958-1963 (Box-folder 13/193)
  - Board of Deacons (Box-folder 13/194)
  - Budget, 1950s (Box-folder 13/195)
  - By Laws (Box-folder 13/196)
  - Church building designs and styles (Box-folder 13/197)
  - Church organization (Box-folder 13/198)
  - Equipment and supplies (Box-folder 13/199)
  - Funding for new building (Box-folder 13/200)
  - Installation of the Rev. Theodore C. Edquist..., 1961 (Box-folder 13/201)
  - Memorials (Box-folder 13/202)
  - Misc. (Box-folder 13/203)
  - New Manse (Box-folder 13/204)
  - Organization (Box-folder 14/205)
  - Pilgrim Firs Camp, 1964 (Box-folder 14/206)
  - Plan of Organization, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 14/207)
  - Sermons (Box-folder 14/208)
  - Ushers (Box-folder 14/209)
  - New Construction
    - Bascom's Cabinet Works, Keene, Texas, pews and chancel furniture (Box-folder 14/210)
    - Blueprints (Box-folder 14/211)
    - Building (Box-folder 14/212)
    - Building committee (Box-folder 14/213)
    - Building program (Box-folder 14/214)
    - Busboom and Rauh, general contractors (Box-folder 14/215)
    - Robert L. Durham, architect (Box-folder 14/216)
    - Furniture--chancel and pews (Box-folder 15/217)
    - Kitchen cabinets and misc. bids (Box-folder 15/218)
    - Misc. invoices, bids, and corr. (Box-folder 15/219)
    - Standifer Refrigeration and Heating (Box-folder 15/220)
- Misc. Pullman and WSC, 6
  - Pullman
    - Recreation, circa 1947 (Box-folder 15/221)
    - Fire Department, 1966 (Box-folder 15/222)
    - Honor Roll, Men Serving in the Armed Forces, 1945 (Box-folder 15/223)
  - WSC
    - Buildings and Grounds Manual (Box-folder 15/224)
    - "Report onthe Use of Space Devoted to Instructional Purposes, First Semester, 1953-54" (Box-folder 15/225)
    - Room Scheduling Procedures, 1950-1951 (Box-folder 15/226)
    - Safety, traffic, parking area (Box-folder 15/227)
    - Space Priorities Committee, meeting minutes, 1954-1958 (Box-folder 15/228)
    - Space Priorities Committee, 1956-1958 (Box-folder 15/229)
    - Traffic Engineering (Box-folder 15/230)
    - Description and date: Speech: The State College of Washington: Its Origin, History, and Present Development, circa 1940-1941 (Box-folder 15/230.1)
- Humor, 7
  - Cartoons, part 1 (Box-folder 15/231)
  - Cartoons, part 2 (Box-folder 16/232)
  - Clippings, misc. (Box-folder 16/233)
  - Heyer Cartoon and Idea Book (Box-folder 16/234)
  - Humor (Box-folder 16/235)
  - Limericks (Box-folder 16/236)
  - Quotes (Box-folder 16/237)
- Social Clubs and Other Organizations, 8
  - Alpha Rho Chi fraternity, misc. (Box-folder 17/238)
  - Alpha Rho Chi fraternity, The Anthem, 1945-1962, inc. (Box-folder 17/239)
  - Alpha Rho Chi fraternity, The Archi, 1939-1960, inc. (Box-folder 17/240)
  - American Automobile Association, Spokane, Wash. (Box-folder 17/241)
  - B.I.L.--P.E.O. (Box-folder 17/242)
  - Camera Club of Pullman, 1965 (Box-folder 17/243)
  - Chamber of Commerce, Pullman, 1925-1964 (Box-folder 17/244)
  - Estes Park, Colorado [YMCA conference], 1965 (Box-folder 17/245)
  - Freemasonry, "General Information Concerning the Ancient and Accepted Scottish Rite of Freemasonry...", [1963] (Box-folder 17/246)
  - Friends of the Library, WSU, 1941-1964 (Box-folder 17/247)
  - Knights Templar, Masonic Lodges (Box-folder 17/248)
  - Quarter Century Club, WSU, 1959-1966 (Box-folder 17/249)
  - Pullman, church, Episcopal [construction] (Box-folder 17/250)
  - Pullman, church, Presbyterian [construction] (Box-folder 17/251)
  - Royal Arch, Masonic Lodges (Box-folder 17/252)
  - Scarab fraternity (Box-folder 17/253)
  - University of Illinois, Class of 1916, 50th Anniversary (Box-folder 17/254)
- Miscellanous, 9
  - American Express Credit Card, 1962-1966 (Box-folder 18/255)
  - Auto Accident enroute to Bellevue, 12-23-1965 (Box-folder 18/256)
  - Automobiles, 1950s-1960s (Box-folder 18/257)
  - Cards--Bridge (Box-folder 18/258)
  - Chinese Rugs, 1931 (Box-folder 18/259)
  - Communism, clippings and pamphlets (Box-folder 18/260)
  - Drafting Machine (Box-folder 18/261)
  - Kappa Alpha Theta sorority [Marge Rounds, pledge, 1950] (Box-folder 18/262)
  - Military Records, World War I discharge (Box-folder 18/263)
  - News clippings
    - John F. Kennedy Assassination, 1963 (Box-folder 18/264)
    - 1964 elections (Box-folder 18/265)
    - 1965-1966 (Box-folder 18/266)
    - A.S.E.E. convention, 1966 (Box-folder 18/267)
    - Pullman people (Box-folder 18/268)
    - Cemetery (Box-folder 18/269)
    - Misc. (Box-folder 18/270)
  - Republican Party, 1960s (Box-folder 18/271)
  - Scale Modeling of Buildings (Box-folder 18/272)
  - Talks--slides, 1965 (Box-folder 18/273)
  - Whitman County Navy certificate (Box-folder 18/274)
  - Margery Rounds drawing, Fred Rounds, jr. (Box-folder 18/275)